episode 11 coherence I'm gonna turn her
just run this one off the top of my head
because correctly trying to harvest can
name it became yes I apologize if the
audio sucks
I've got a friend a local friend who's
volunteered to come in and help him set
this thing absolutely onion doesn't suck
and it is too bothersome I'll just
reshoot this whole thing but in the
meantime this glue shop so coherent in
order to do that concept we have to
actually do a different concept called
resonance and this one I think is pretty
easy I've got some experience metaphors
and seems to work so well for residences
just use the metaphor of tuning into an
old analogue radio station fm
so you've got a 99.7 who's the radio
station and you would do it for
broadcasting a signal in the
electromagnetic spectrum we're pumping a
lot of energy to that signal but then
the receiver if they're even slightly
off the frequency it just as it was
notice you're just you're turning the
dial here 97 98 99 9 then one minute
which is still just static all the ones
no signal you get to 99.5 and maybe you
start here just the edge of signal right
9.6 and okay now I can hear the station
in a business station there's still a
huge amount of noise in it
98.7 and bam you're locked and you can
just hear almost all certain tone almost
of noise and so you're right your
receiver and the transmitter are the
same rustic frequency and bam the amount
of energy this converted is signal just
as a massive spike resonance system has
that characteristic out very low signal
to noise and a big spike where the
resonance frequency happens to be and
this is a profoundly important
characteristic reality if you're in a
system that has resonance as teachers
then a couple of things are just
straight-up required if you are out of
resonance then the only meaningful thing
to do is to figure out how to get
interest because otherwise you're just
basically wasted on your energy want
something which is a massive amount of
coolant or heat if you like
light comparison and then by contest if
you could find a residence frequency
then you can actually do stuff like
interesting things can happen that
otherwise might not seem possible at all
because this massive game can happen
residency
okay so so so with resonance we can now
start talking about the concept of
coherence when I lied to you is going
build it up in series of stages and I'll
do coherence in the in the domain of
people since that's the object that I I
care about although it might also be
useful that you switch out their domain
just to get the concept little bit
richer so imagine you've got a room the
room has say 10 15 20 people in it and
let's go ahead and just assign each
discrete individual a level of
sovereignty from episode 10 sovereignty
obviously using an integer any kind of
metric to define sovereignty is already
travesty but for purposes of this let's
just do it let's say just everybody has
a sovereign team of five okay so now now
the individuals are in this group
they're floating about and tuna digits
just call them a and B they may somehow
come into each other's awareness there's
a some connection communication event
occurs so it's definitely with coherence
is communication there's a very very
light communication so it's just the
channel that's forming has a channel
bandwidth of one it's just the lowest
level possible communication between the
two at at this point a choice event
occurs either they can endeavor to
increase their communication bandwidth
which in this case might be going from
eye contact to walking up towards each
other and beginning a conversation or
they can just continue to just go there
and wet and the communication breaks
down back so so this is true the choice
is made now moved into a stronger
communication so now what's happening is
that there's a whole bunch of stuff
going on which broadly speaking is
mostly most important aspects are in
fact endeavouring to figure out how to
find what a residents frequency might be
lat
various kinds of articulations language
sending over big packages concepts
because obviously as human beings the
the metaphor resonant frequency isn't
just in say two communication channel
itself it's also in the state of the
consciousness the state of the model on
either side and how those states acts
for themselves in or out of residence
you know so we can find get on the same
page and build a shared language and
become increasingly sensitive to how
given individual expresses themselves
like you know how does how do i express
myself through facial expressions that
are express myself through hands tone of
voice words forms body language etc etc
we can build the capacity for doing
exchange and I'm going to call this
relation so we're coming into
relationship and that's at stage two so
to the degree to which we spend the time
and effort and have skills on this or
just pure luck of the draw it may
actually do come into relationship a
week we shift into something in the
domain of resonance then what happens of
course is that the the channel opens up
why is and say instead of a
communication channel one we now have a
communication channel eight and now at
this point we're entering into something
where we have the ability to relate to
each other in a generative fashion and
I'm going to call that coordination so
we're able to communicate effectively to
communicate quite well and as a
consequence we can actually share
information and we can share state and
we're able to do things that are near to
our mutual benefit so now we're at the
stage of coordination and that's a good
place to be and you can look at
agreements and we can make choices that
are compatible and self reinforcing but
we're now at another choice threshold at
this level we now have a possibility of
moving into the process of actually
generating hearings and what happens
when you move into the space of
coherence is that there was in fact an
emergent property that that develops it
may sound a bit esoteric and just ways
that you can actually make it sound less
esoteric was just DNA cetera to me for
now what
there's a synergy value that develops
where the relationship itself begins to
have its own qualities of sovereignty as
its own agency its own perception its
own sense making which is more than the
sum of the parts
so in coordination we give this in a
very light way that there's some kind of
win-win synergy they can merge in
coherence that synergy action begins to
have its own sovereignty and so you
might say for example that in
coordination we maybe have increased the
sovereignty of a and B from five and
five to six and six so each individual
sovereignty has increased in coherence
we're now beginning to have a process
whereby there's an a as a B and there's
a union of a and B and so if a is it six
because it's a put the Union maybe isn't
one this is a new thing a new phenomenon
a new sovereignty in reality that is
happening as a consequence of the
increasing quality and qualities of the
relationship between the two matey
now the the next move and the kind of
key move that makes coherence finally
come into place is that precisely to the
degree that this new sovereignty
exercises its agency so as to reinforce
the ongoing relationship and the quality
of that relationship such that it
increases the sovereignty of the
relationship so it's a it's a recurrent
the relationship begins to have its own
sovereignty it emerges as a phenomenal
and and then it actually has the ability
to use its sovereignty to maintain and
increase the quality of its sovereignty
and so now we're in connect you have
something where there's a bottoms-up
causation the individuals and
relationship generating subjected to
something now as he bought a top down in
causation that conditions the
relationship so as to maintain the
existence of the shifting domain we
might have mentioned for example
organelles in a Cell I was fear Tomic
eaters the organelles but now there's a
cell membrane the cell membrane
generates a feedback the conditions the
continuing presence of the organelles in
relationship with each other so the
owner knows a relationship give rights
the potential would there be set the
conditions of the cell though they give
rise to the route the coordination the
relationships dividual organelles and
this whole thing back and forth
isn't that coherent we can also do this
in the context of state at the bottom
which is just a macro version the
previous set got a whole bunch of cells
my own genetic cells as well as my
microbial and all the other bacteria
that course throughout my body and each
one has its own agency as an individual
cell but and together they coordinate to
generate the possibility space that
shows it as my body like my tissues my
my organs and the whole system that
hangs together but then that system
generates a series of causal effects
that maintain the possibility and the
coordination of the individual cells and
so this whole thing is coherent and
system
and if that guy said then you could just
say you've got a you've got B you've got
you innovative AMD and you have the
ability of the Union to have causal
effect on a and B and you have a because
of the causal effect on eating
appearance people sovereign TVA the
sovereignty of the sovereignty team so
then there's a another possible stage I
think it's important to get this
distinction because otherwise people
might throw was Plast and that is
community I'm just gonna on the ecology
what I mean by Communion is a
circumstance where the larger system I
call it the whole or the Union not only
maintains the integrity of the
relationships so as to continue itself
but it does so in a fashion that
actually reduces the sovereignty of the
lower level importance the individuals a
and B thus also the bodies of this so if
the body is a form of communion where
the cells do course still have some
sovereignty but their sovereignty as
cells is quite constrained by virtue of
being in the community known as the body
otherwise they'll show those cancer
cells and the police the mutant system
identify that this be in violation
destroy and so there are forms of that
that's a form work where you're
different coordination coherence to
communion and you know sometimes that's
what selected for that works but it's
important to recognize that coherence is
not community it's a different state but
coordination you've got to mean you've
got prepared and this is this piece is
really important the reason why
coherence is able to maintain is
precisely the degree to which
participating in the relationship
actually is a good choice for the
members of the relationship that by
virtue of being relationship my
sovereignty increases my capacity to
make good choices increases and so it's
a is simply a consequence of my choice
by this thing that's going here it
continues to maintain not coercively but
actually just because it is in fact a
good choice for the members to continue
to participate and and the way
the system maintains that is by virtue
of just providing that so you might
imagine for example you know just a
classic example being in a good
relationship if you're in a good
relationship the relationship is
committed to the continuing increase of
the well-being of the sovereignty of the
members of the relationship so by virtue
of being in the relationship you're just
doing better than not and so it's just a
good choice and by virtue of being in
the relationship because you're in
relationship you are able to afford the
capacity to improve your well-being so
we just kind of this awesome constant
feedback positive improvement and that's
the sweet spot right you don't have to
follow them to communion and you don't
have to default to coordination there is
this thing coherence and this is the
fabric out of which any viable future
society must be built it's the sweet
spot through the agency and communion is
coherence well I think that's that we
can talk a lot about what are the tools
the toolkits of coherence building
things like awareness and then it's self
awareness and then relationship words
things like discernment skillfulness in
communication and agreement formation in
a relationship building and strength
coherence can actually be measured in
strength which is the degree to which
the the coherence can endure forces that
are pushing on it while maintaining its
own integrity so these are all may be
things to talk about in another video if
that's the interest